新喋喋人生
第一季  第六集
糖罐里的薯条
今天早上我刚接过她手中的茶  她说道
I'd just taken her tea up this morning when she said,
"格雷厄姆  我非常爱你"
"Graham, I think the world of you."
我说  "我也非常爱你"
I said, "I think the world of you."
她说  "那就没事了"
She said, "That's all right, then."
我说  "怎么突然说起这个"
I said, "What's brought this on?"
她说  "没什么
She said, "Nothing.
这个茶看上去很浓  拉开窗帘吧"
"This tea looks strong, pull the curtains."
当然  我知道她为什么突然这么说
Of course, I knew what had brought it on.
她说  "我不想让你觉得自己不是最好的"
She said, "I wouldn't want you to think you're not number one."
我说  "你对我来说也是最好的
I said, "Well, you're number one with me, too.
把你的假牙给我  我清洗一下"
"Give me your teeth and I'll swill 'em."
事实上  我们昨天有点兴奋
What it was, we'd had a spot of excitement yesterday,
我们偶然重温了一段她以前的日子
we ran into a bit of mother's past.
我对她说  "我居然不知道你还有这样一段过去"
I said to her, "I didn't know you had a past.
我以为我就是你的过去"  她说  "就你"
"I thought I was your past." She said, "You?"
我说  "好吧  我们毕竟相处很久了
I said, "Well, we go back a long way.
和父亲相比他哪里好啊"  她笑了
"Where does he fit in vis-a-vis Dad?" She laughed.
"他是你爸之前那"个  我说  "我爸之前
"Oh, he was pre-Dad." I said, "Pre-Dad?
我很惊讶你竟然还记得他
"I'm surprised you remember him.
你连关掉电热毯都能忘"
"You don't remember to switch your blanket off."
她说  "那不一样
She said, "That's different.
他的名字是特恩布尔"
"His name's Turnbull."
我说  "我知道  他说过"
I said, "I know. He said."
我让她坐在战争纪念碑旁那个她常坐的位子上
I'd parked her by the war memorial in her usual seat while I went
我去拿一些读物回来
and got some reading matter.
然后我又等她
Then I waited while she went
花了一便士去上残疾人厕所
and spent a penny in the disabled toilet.
她并不是真的残疾  她只是记性不好  但她却说
She's not actually disabled - her memory's bad, but she says
她喜欢用残疾人厕所因为那里的活动空间更大
she prefers using their toilets because you get more elbow room.
她总爱花很长时间摆弄双手或者什么东西
She always takes forever, diddling her hands and whatnot,
后来她终于回来了  原来是一直在
and when she eventually comes back, it turns out she's been
跟服务员聊天
chatting to the attendant.
我说  "聊什么呢"  她说  "绞刑
I said, "What about?" She said, "Hanging.
她赞成对轻罪加重处罚
"She was in favour of stiffer penalties for minor offences
而我认为  我们更清楚这件事  我们格雷厄姆和我
"and I thought, 'Well, we know better, our Graham and me.'
当时你也在就好了  亲爱的  你可以给她
"I wish you'd been there, love - you could have given her
好好讲讲统计数据  我们去哪里喝茶"
"the statistics. Where are we going for our tea?"
我妈是这样的  尽管她并没有经历过
The thing about Mam is that, even though she's never had
正规的教育  但她在我身边耳濡目染
a proper education, she's picked up enough from me
可以在讨论比如环境和色彩这种
to be able to hold her own in discussions on up-to-the-minute
当下流行话题中坚持自己的观点了
topics like the environment and the colour problem, and for
在她的年龄和背景下  她的自由主义倾向很严重
a woman of her age and background, she has a very liberal slant.
她能一边盯着我的监护人一边只为自己考虑
She'll look at my Guardian and she actually thinks for herself.
乔杜里医生跟我说  "要注意  格雷厄姆
Dr Chaudhury said to me, "Full marks, Graham.
避免髋部骨折的最好方法是拥有一个灵活的头脑"
"The best way to avoid a broken hip is to have a flexible mind."
战争纪念碑那里的人群开始闹事
They go mad round the war memorial
所以我们经过的时候
so when we cross over,
我通常会挽着她的手臂  直到我们
I'll generally put my arm through hers until
安全穿过那里  只要我们走上人行道
we're safely across, only once we're on the pavement,
她就会故意拖着不肯撒手
she'll postpone letting it go,
因为有一次我们被一个发调查问卷的女人
because once upon a time we got stopped by one of these
拦住了  以为我们是一对夫妻
questionnaire women who reckons to take us for husband and wife.
我妈都有白头发了
I mean, Mam's got white hair!
她当时想故伎重演  我说"妈  松开我的胳膊"
She was doing this dodge and I said, "Mam, let go of my arm."
我真的没有用力挣脱
I didn't really wrench it,
结果她突然平躺在人行道上
only next thing I knew she's flat on the pavement.
我说  "天啊  妈"
I said, "Oh, my God, Mother!"
人们围聚过来  我捡起她的包
People gather round I pick up her bag,
她坐起来  说道  "我的长筒袜都拉丝了"
and she sits up and says, "I've laddered both my stockings!"
我说"别管长筒袜了  你的骨盆还好吗"
I said, "Never mind your stockings, what about your pelvis?"
她说  "都怪这个双光眼镜
She said, "It's these bifocals.
他们都说了你不能往下看  我在躲避呕吐物"
"They tell you not to look down. I was avoiding some sick."
旁边有人说  "这声音好熟悉"
Somebody says, "That's a familiar voice,"
然后就有一个小个子俯身对着她
and there's a little fella bending over her,
戴着绿色毡帽  身穿短雨衣
green trilby hat, shorty raincoat.
"你好"  他说  "还记得我吗"
"Hello," he says, "remember me?"
她可记不住人
Well, she doesn't remember people,
我可以肯定  因为她向我发誓她没见过
I know for a fact, because she swore me down she'd never met
乔伊·巴克尔  她在我的日间护理站
Joy Buckle, who teaches Flowers
教毛毡织物编花课
in Felt and Fabric at my day centre.
我跟她说  "你认识乔伊
I said to her, "You have met Joy,
你还给她织了一个茶壶套呢"
cos you knitted her a tea cosy."
她只会织这些东西  茶壶套
That's all she can knit, tea cosies.
还有睡袜  都是过时的老物件了
And bed socks. Both outmoded articles.
我跟她说  "拓展下吧
I said to her, "Branch out.
如果你能织茶壶套  你也可以织滑雪帽"
"If you can knit tea cosies, you can knit skiing hats."
她说  "好吧  我会织的"
She said, "Well, I will."
只是我必须要监督她
Only I have to stand over her
不然她还是会给自己留好退路
or else she'll still leave a hole for the spout.
我说  "你认识乔伊  你记得她
Anyway, I said, "You have met Joy, you do remember her
因为你说她长了一对令人震惊的眉毛"
"because you said she had some shocking eyebrows."
她说  "你可别把这话跟她说"
She said, "I hope you didn't tell her that."
我说  "我当然没说"  她说"那我就不记得了"
I said, "Of course I didn't." She said, "Well, I don't remember."
她就是这样  她记不住
And that's how she is, she doesn't remember
而这个小个子却还在说  "你还记得我吗"
and there's this little fella saying, "Do you remember me?"
我说"不  她不记得了  走吧妈  我扶你起来"
I said, "No, she won't. Come on, Mother. Let's get you up."
可她却说  "记得你  当然了  弗兰克·特恩布尔嘛
Only she says, "Remember you? "Of course. It's Frank Turnbull!
得有50年了吧"  他说  "52年了
"Must be 50 years!" He says, "52."
法利  1934年"
"Filey, 1934."
她说  "海峰"  他说  "卧室没有一粒沙"
She said, "Sea Crest." He said, "No sand in the bedrooms."
然后他们一起哈哈大笑
And they both cracked out laughing.
这个时候她还是坐在冰冷的地上不肯起来
Meanwhile, she's still stuck on the cold pavement.
我说  "快点  妈
I said, "Come along, Mother.
痔疮可不是好东西"  可他又插嘴了
"We don't want piles." Only he butts in again.
他说  "恕我直言  我建议在挪动一个人之前
He said, "With respect, it's advisable not to move a person
要先确定这个人的骨头没有断
"until it's been ascertained no bones are broken.
我曾经在圣约翰急救队干过"
"I was in the St John's Ambulance Brigade."
"对"  母亲说  "你在谁身上学会了绑绷带来着"
"Yes," said Mother, "and who did you learn your bandaging on?"
他们又大笑起来
And they burst out laughing again.
他戴着明黄色的手套  可能之前当过赌注登记员
He had on these bright yellow gloves - could have been a bookie.
最后我环抱着她的腰部把她抬了起来
Eventually, I get my arms around her waist and hoist her up,
可那位大人却帮不上忙  因为他说自己后背不好
only his lordship's no help as he claims to have a bad back.
当我终于让她站起来后
When I've finally restored her to the perpendicular,
她开始介绍他
she introduces him.
"这位是弗兰克·特恩布尔"  她说
"This is Frank Turnbull," she said,
"我过去的一个老朋友"
"A friend of mine from the old days."
什么过去  我第一次知道还有过去这么一说
What old days? First time I knew there were any old days.
结果他是个男士服装店的老板  半退休
Turns out he's a gents' outfitter, semi-retired,
在布拉德福德有店面  在莫克姆开了类似卖折扣品的店
shop in Bradford and some sort of outlet in Morecambe.
我想"这样的话黄手套就好解释了"
I thought, "Well, that accounts for the yellow gloves."
他马上占据主导地位
Straight off, he takes charge.
"薇拉  你现在需要的是一杯咖啡"
"What you need now, Vera, is a cup of coffee."
我说"我们刚才就是要去喝茶  是吧妈"
I said, "We were just going for some tea, weren't we, Mother?"
薇拉
Vera!
她的名字不是薇拉  从没有人叫她薇拉
Her name's not Vera. She's never been called Vera.
我爸从来没叫她薇拉  除了有一次
My dad never called her Vera, except just once,
我妈用轮椅推着他进剧院
when they were wheeling him into theatre.
薇拉
Vera?
"好"  他说  "跟我走"
"Right," he says, "follow me."
挽着她的胳膊
Puts his arm through hers.
"注意点"  她说  "你会惹得我男朋友吃醋了"
"Careful," she said. "You'll make my boyfriend jealous."
我一句话都没说
I didn't say anything.
我们通常会去的那家咖啡店
Now, the cafe that we generally patronise...
稍微有点不同
..is just that bit different.
装修很简单  但是很高级
It's plain, but it's classy,
桌面上没有桌布
no cloths on the tables,
菜单是在一小块石板上
the menu comes on a little slate
服务员穿着他们自己的服装
and the waitresses wear their own clothes
看起来仿佛只是来这里体验生活的
and look as if they're doing it just for the fun of it.
一切食物都是手工自制的  我们俩都超爱
The stuff's all home-made and we're both big fans
那家的海枣核桃面包
of the date and walnut bread.
我说  "这家到了"
I said, "This is the place."
特恩布尔先生径直走过了这家店
Mr Turnbull goes straight past.
"不"  他说  "我知道有个地方  刚开业
"No," he says, "I know somewhere, just opened.
继续前进"
"Press on."
如果有一件事是母亲和我
Now, if there's one thing that Mother
一致认同的  那就是红色是个很普通的颜色
and me are agreed on, it's that red is a common colour.
而这个地方从里到外没有一处不是红色的
And this whole place is done out in red.
灯罩是红的
Lampshades red,
服务员的衣服是红的  盘子是红的
waitresses in red, plates red,
桌子上那些装着酱料的塑料瓶子  搞得像
and on the tables, those plastic sauce things got up
西红柿一样  也是红的
to look like tomatoes - also red.
而且我看到  糖罐里还有一根薯条
And when I look, there's a chip in the sugar.
我想  母亲不会喜欢这种地方的
I thought, "Mother won't like this."
可她却说  "这里看起来好欢快  不是吗  格雷厄姆"
Only she says, "This looks cheerful, dun't it, Graham?"
我说  糖罐里有根薯条
I said, "There's a chip in the sugar."
"观察很细"  他说  "他们还在面临着
"A detail," he says, "They're still
创业初期的种种困难
having their teething troubles.
三杯咖啡吗"  我说  "我们喝茶"
"Is it three coffees?" I said, "We like tea."
可母亲却说  "不
Only Mother says, "No.
我想要冒险  我要咖啡"
"I feel like an adventure. I'll have coffee."
他拿着菜单  然后把手放在她的手上
He gets hold of the menu and puts his hand on hers.
"我可以推荐一个芝士汉堡吗"
"Might I suggest," he said, "a cheeseburger?"
她说  "那是什么"
"Oh," she said, "what's that?"
他说  "新鲜的牧场牛肉
He said, "It's fresh country beef,
夹杂着煎得金黄的洋葱  上面是烤芝士
"mingled with golden-fried onions, topped off with toasted
还搭配了炸薯条和柠檬角"
"cheese and served with French fries and lemon wedge."
"柠檬角"  母亲说
"Ooh, lemon wedge," said Mother.
"听起来不错"
"That sounds nice."
我心想  "我倒希望你能吃下去
I thought, "Well, I hope you can keep it down."
因为上次吃披萨的故事会再来一遍"
"Because it'll be the pizza story all over again."
一口披萨  凌晨四点
One mouthful and at four o'clock in the morning,
我还坐在她床边抱着桶让她吐
I'm still stuck at her bedside with the bucket.
她说  "我喜欢在食物上冒险
She said, "I like new adventures in eating.
有一次我还吃了披萨  是不是  格雷厄姆"
"I had a pizza once, didn't I, Graham?"
我什么话都没说
I didn't say anything.
点的餐上了  她在埋头大吃
They fetch the food and she's wiring in.
他说"你的芝士汉堡还喜欢吗"  她说"喜欢
He said, "Are you enjoying your cheeseburger?" She said, "I am.
那个东西应该是番茄汁吧"
"Would I be mistaken in thinking that's tomato sauce?"
他说"是的"  她说  "给我们挤一坨"
He said, "It is." She says, "Give us a squirt."
他们大笑起来
They burst out laughing.
他说  "格雷厄姆  玻璃杯子
He said, "Glass cups, Graham.
当心  不然我会看到你的鼻孔"  他们又笑了
"Careful or I'll see up your nose." More laughter.
她说  "格雷厄姆很有教养
She said, "Graham's quite refined.
他经常会喝一杯干雪莉酒"
"He often has a dry sherry."
"他大可以打扮得再潇洒点"  特恩布尔先生说
"Well, he could do with smartening up a bit," said Mr Turnbull.
"塑料雨衣吗
"Plastic mack?
你会想穿一件那种絮棉的衣服
"You want to get one of these quilted jobs,
我卖了很多件那样的"
"I've shifted a lot of those."
我说"我不喜欢那种絮棉衣服"
"I don't like those quilted jobs," I said.
"他爱出汗"  母亲说
"He sweats," Mother said.
"现在这个年纪和时代  这个理由
"There's no excuse for that
可不成立"  特恩布尔先生说
in this day and age," said Mr Turnbull.
"市面上的制剂各种各样
"The range of preparations on the market.
你可以买进一些滚珠
"You want to invest in some roll-on
除臭剂"  声音大的谁都能听见
deodorant." Everybody could hear.
"喇叭裤太讨人厌了  在布拉德福德也是"
"And flares are anathema, even in Bradford."
"格雷厄姆不介意的  对吧"  母亲说
"Oh, Graham doesn't mind, do you, Graham?" said Mother.
"他经常读书"  "那又怎样"  特恩布尔先生说
"He reads a lot." "So what?" said Mr Turnbull.
"我知道好几个大作家
"I know several big readers
还在想方设法成为交际家
who still manage to be men about town.
黄绿色是个很漂亮的色度
"Lovat green is a nice shade.
这么跟你说吧  格雷厄姆
"I'll tell you this, Graham," he said,
要是我在市中心护卫一位
"if I were squiring a young lady
年轻的小姐出行  我不会
"like this around town, I wouldn't
选择穿灰袜子配凉鞋
do it in grey socks and sandals."
这双鞋子是意大利产的  你看这材质"
"These shoes are Italian. Feel."
"我总是以为格雷厄姆会成为一名很好的牧师"
"I always think Graham would have made a good parson..."
母亲说  一边打量他的脚
Mother said...feeling his foot...
"只不过他不信上帝"
"..only he doesn't believe in God."
特恩布尔先生说"这如今不是什么硬性条件
"Oh, that's no handicap these days," said Mr Turnbull.
你是干什么的"
"What do you do?"
母亲说"他现在还在找工作
"He's between jobs at present," said Mother.
他之前给残障儿童做毛绒玩具
"He used to do soft toys for handicapped children.
后来有段时间做纸花"
"Then he was making paper flowers at one stage."
我去了厕所
I went to the toilet.
当我回来的时候他说"我不相信有精神疾病这一说
When I came back, he said, "I don't believe in mental illness.
十有八九就是没打起精神罢了"
"Nine times out of ten it's a case of pulling your socks up."
我什么都没说
I didn't say anything.
"是啊"  母亲说  "对这事的看法都太偏激了"
"Yes," said Mother, "the pendulum's gone too far."
她甚至没看我一眼
She didn't look at me.
"就像那些女孩子  不吃东西"  他说
"It's like these girls, not eating," he said,
"她们要是像我们那样没吃没喝得长大
"They'd eat if they'd been brought
薇拉  肯定没什么是不吃的"
up like us, Vera, nothing to eat."
"对"  她说  "她们活得太容易了"
"Yes," she said, "they have it too easy."
"你结婚了吗"  "两次
"Did you marry?" "Twice," he said.
去年五月我送走了艾米
"I buried Amy last May.
我当时很伤心但生活还是要继续
"I was heartbroken but life has to go on.
我有个儿子住在斯蒂夫尼奇
"I've a son lives in Stevenage.
有两个孙子  其中一个会开摩托车了
"I've got two grandsons - one at the motorbike stage!
你会开吗"  我说"不会"
"Do you drive?" "No," I said.
她说"你会  格雷厄姆  不是有辆小摩托吗"
She said, "You do, Graham, you had that scooter."
我说  那就是个电动自行车
I said, "It was only a moped."
她说"好吧  电动的  那格雷厄姆
She said, "Well, a moped, then Graham.
它们都是一样的
"They're all the same.
我可不能只让他一个人吹牛皮"
"I can't get him to blow his own trumpet."
特恩布尔先生说  "我有一辆罗孚2000  操控感棒极了
"I've got a Rover 2000," said Mr Turnbull, "handles like a dream.
我对精神疾病的解决办法是大量的体力劳动
"My solution to mental illness is hard physical work.
编织拉菲草垫  那我会疯的"
"Making raffia mats, I'd go mad."
"是啊"  母亲说  "他们也做陶器
"Yes," says Mother, "only they do pottery as well.
我见过一些很好看的烟灰缸"
"I've seen some nice ashtrays."
特恩布尔先生说  "绣花枕头
"Feather bedding!" said Mr Turnbull.
你喜欢这些巴基斯坦人吗"
"Do you like these Pakistanis?"
还行吧  母亲说
"Well, in moderation," Mother said.
"我们有个报刊经销商人挺不错的
"We have a nice newsagent.
格雷厄姆觉得我们都一样"
"Graham thinks we're all the same."
我说"我以为你是这么想的"
I said, "I thought you did."
她说"你好好跟我解释的话我会这么想的  格雷厄姆
She said, "I do when you explain it all to me, Graham,
然后我忘了你的解释  又回到原点了"
"and then I forget the explanation and I'm back to square one."
"没有什么好解释的"  特恩布尔先生说
"There is no explanation," Mr Turnbull said.
"他们在我们的邮局里卖芒果
"They sell mangoes in our Post Office -
那该怎么解释"
"what explanation is there for that?"
"我知道"  母亲说  "我还在妇女天地闻到了咖喱味
"I know," Mother said, "I smelled curry on my Woman's Own."
你得很有教养才能理解"
"You have to be educated to understand."
我什么话都没说
I didn't say anything.
他把我们送回家  答应下次来我家附近的时候
He ran us home, promised to give her a tinkle next time
会给她打电话
he was in the neighbourhood.
说他经常在这片地方买双色羊毛衫
Said he was often in the area tracking down two-tone cardigans.
他说  "你母亲是位伟大的女性
He said, "Your Mother is a grand woman.
你要珍惜她"
"You want to cherish her."
"他有的  有的"  母亲说
"He does, he does," Mother said.
"你是我的男朋友  是不是  格雷厄姆"
"You're my boy friend, aren't you, Graham?"
然后她挽住了我的手臂
And she put her arm through mine.
肯定是有哪里闹饥荒  因为我们的
There must be a famine on somewhere because we were just
午饭才刚下肚
letting our midday meal go down
教区牧师就打电话说有几封信要给我们
when the vicar calls with some envelopes.
他穿着厚夹克和运动鞋像风一样闯进来  说道
He breezes in, anorak and running shoes, and he says,
"我想拜访很久了  惠特克太太"
"I always look forward to coming to this house, Mrs Whittaker."
他不知道从哪听说的她聋了  但她并没有
He's got the idea she's deaf, which she's not -
也是她少数几个没毛病的地方
it's one of the few things she isn't.
他说  "你知道为什么吗
He says, "Do you know why?
因为你们二位让我想起
"Because you two remind me
耶稣和他的母亲"
of Jesus and his mother."
我一直以为耶稣对他母亲
Well, I've always thought Jesus
有一点不尊重
was a bit off-hand with his mother,
我记得有的故事里他对她还挺傲慢的
and on one occasion I remember he was quite snotty with her,
但我没说什么
but I didn't say anything.
当然了  老太太是非常高兴的
And of course, Madam is over the moon.
在她的书里如果不能和伊丽莎白王太后相提并论
In her book, if you can't get compared with the Queen Mother,
那么和圣母玛利亚并肩也是好的
the Virgin Mary's the next best thing.
她说  "你结婚了吗"  每次见面都要问他
She says, "Are you married?" Asks him every time.
从不记得  他说  "没有  惠特克太太
Never remembers. He said, "No, Mrs Whittaker.
我和上帝一起"
"I am married to God."
她说  "那你还用做什么家务活呢"
She said, "Where does that leave you with the housework?"
他说  "我做的没有你们家格雷厄姆好
He said, "Well, I don't do as well as your Graham.
他把这里收拾得像个宫殿"
"He's got this place like a palace."
她说  "我的活是我自己干的
"Well," she said, "I do my whack.
我今天早上洗了四双长筒袜"  她没有
"I washed four pairs of stockings this morning." She hadn't.
她只是把袜子放进桶里  然后就从她脑子里消失了
She'd put them in the bowl then they slipped her mind,
具体的操作就只能交给我了
so the operation devolved on me.
他说  "您今天感觉怎么样  惠特克太太"
He said, "How are you today, Mrs Whittaker?"
她说  "半边身体感觉很僵硬"
She said, "Stiff down one side."
我说"她昨天摔了一跤"  她说"我从来不摔跤"
I said, "She had a fall yesterday." She said, "I never did."
我说  "你摔了  妈
I said, "You did, Mother.
你摔了一跤  然后就碰见了特恩布尔先生"
"You had a fall, then you ran into Mr Turnbull."
她说  "是哦  是这样的"
She said, "Oh, yeah...that's right."
开始在她的包里翻找口红
Starts rooting in her bag for her lipstick.
她说  "你穿的就是那种厚夹克了对吧
She said, "That's one of them anoraky things, isn't it?
那已经过时了
"They've gone out now, those."
要是想穿得像个交际家  你要
"If you want to look like a man about town, you want to get
买件欧陆式鸭绒被"
"one of those continental quilts."
他说  "什么"  我说"她意思是棉衣"
He said, "Oh?" I said, "She means those quilted jackets."
她说  "他懂我"
She said, "He knows what I mean.
"那是什么鞋子"  他说  "这是训练鞋"
"And what are those shoes?!" He said, "They're training shoes."
"训练什么  你还不够资格吗"
"Training for what? Are you not fully qualified?"
他说  "如果耶稣还活着  惠特克太太
He said, "If Jesus were alive today, Mrs Whittaker, I think
我想你会发现他就穿着这种鞋子"
"you'd find these are the type of shoes he'd be wearing."
她说"如果他母亲还管他就不会了
"Not if his mother had anything to do with it," she said.
她会让他脱掉斯特德和辛普森鞋子
"She'd have him down Stead and Simpson's
换上好的烤花皮鞋
"and get him into some good brogues.
有人跟我说意大利人的鞋子做得很好"
"Somebody was telling me the Italians make good shoes."
牧师把这点作为自己开始宣讲
The vicar takes this as his cue
有些人连一双鞋子都没有的信号
to start on about people with no shoes
再借此谈到埃塞俄比亚的饥荒
at all and, via this, to the famine in Ethiopia.
我勉强给了50便士  他告诉我
I fork out 50p, which he tells me
这够六户人家吃一周了
will feed six families for a week,
她说  "本来能给我买点花街巧克力的"
and she says, "Well, could have bought me some Quality Street."
当他走到门口时  他说
When he's at the door, he says,
"我要向你致敬  格雷厄姆  我也有母亲"
"I take my hat off to you, Graham, I've got a mother myself."
当我进门她说  "牧师
When I get back in she said, "Vicar!
叫他报童还差不多
"He looks more like the paper boy.
你怎么会正眼看一个鞋子没鞋带的人呢"
"How can you look up to somebody in pumps?"
正在这时有人敲门了
Just then there's a knock at the door.
她说"快趴下  他回来了"
She said, "Get down, he's back."
可惜并不是
Only it isn't.
是特恩布尔先生
It's Mr Turnbull.
这次换了一套行头
New outfit this time -
麂皮小夹克  灯芯绒衣领
little suede jacket, corduroy collar,
栗色裤子
maroon trousers.
她说  "你穿得真鲜艳"
She said, "You're colourful."
"没有  只是刚好休闲裤在打折而已"  他说
"No, we just happened to have these slacks on offer," he said.
"不知道你想不想去一趟博尔顿修道院呢"
"I wondered if you fancied a run out to Bolton Abbey?"
她说  "博尔顿修道院
She said, "Oh, Bolton Abbey?"
就在我家这条街前面  是吧格雷厄姆
"That's right up our street, isn't it, Graham?
格雷厄姆对古建筑很了解  不是吗格雷厄姆
"Graham's good with old buildings, aren't you, Graham?
了解各个时期的房屋
"Knows all the periods of houses.
有个时期最近正流行
"There's one period that's just come in.
其他人都不喜欢  但我们喜欢"
"Other people don't like it yet, but we do, don't we?"
我说"我不知道"  她说"你知道  是什么时期"
I said, "I don't know." She said, "You do. What, is it?"
"维多利亚"
"Victorian".
"就是这个"  她说  "维多利亚"]
"That's it!" she said, "Victorian."
可惜很多建筑都被拆毁了"
"Only there's a lot been pulled down."
特恩布尔打了个哈欠
Mr Turnbull yawns.
他说  "我有个小平房"
He said, "I've got a little bungalow."
她说  "那真好
She said, "Oh, that's nice.
我喜欢漂亮的小平房  你呢  格雷厄姆"
"I like a nice bungalow. Don't you, Graham?"
我说  "喜欢  只要不在破坏风景的地方就行"
I said, "Yes, provided it's not a blot on the landscape."
他说  "我的平房是建筑师设计的
He said, "Mine's architect-designed.
有个露台和一个早餐吧台
"It's got a patio and a breakfast bar,
往下能俯瞰到美丽的风景"
it overlooks a beauty spot."
她说  "那听起来棒极了
"Oh," she said, "That sounds tip-top.
我们最好带上冰鞋  格雷厄姆"
"We'd better be getting our skates on, Graham."
他说  "我在伊尔克利的时候
He said, "I've got to pick up
已经在车上已经装了很多
a load of green three-quarter-length
绿色中袖防风夹克
wind-cheaters in Ilkley.
真的没有第三个人坐的地方了
"We won't really have room for a third party.
想看什么书上的图片里不是都有吗"
"Isn't there anything on at the pictures?"
她说  "他会很乐意看书的  是吧亲爱的"
"Oh," she said, "He'll be happy reading, won't you, love?"
"反正你这个年纪也不想每时每刻都陪在你母亲
"Anyway," said Mr Turnbull, "you don't
身边的  对吧  格雷厄姆"  特恩布尔先生说
"always want to be with your Mother at your age, do you, Graham?"
我什么都没说
I didn't say anything.
我一直躺在我的床上
I've been laid on my bed...
看着一本杂志
..reading one of my magazines.
我有种感觉  有人在盯着这栋房子
I've a feeling somebody's looking at the house,
只不过我看不到是谁
only I can't see anybody.
有一两次我觉得听到了敲门声
And once or twice I think I've heard a knock at the door,
但我没有起身
but I haven't gone...
万一门口没人呢
..in case there's nobody there.
今天他们去了约克镇
Today, they went over to York.
他把她送回家的时候已经七点了
It was after seven when he dropped her off.
通常他都会进屋的  但今天没有
Generally he comes in, but not today.
只是轻轻地亲吻了她
Just gives her a little kiss.
她得弯下腰
She has to bend down.
我说  "你们玩得开心吗"  她说"开心
I said, "Did you have a nice time?" She said, "Yes.
我们吃了鸡蛋和薯条  茶  面包和黄油
"We had egg and chips, tea, bread and butter.
我们有很多共同点  那还有一个新的大停车场"
"We've got a lot in common and there's a grand new car park."
我说  "你们进大教堂了吗"  她说"没有
I said, "Did you go in the Minster?" She said, "No.
弗兰克不喜欢古建筑
"Frank's not keen on old buildings.
觉得我们应该多看看未来
"Thinks we need to look more to the future.
他说布拉德福德开了个新的步行商业区
"He says there's a spanking new precinct in Bradford,
所以下次就去那里
"so that's next on the agenda!
你怎么不说话"
"You're quiet."
我说  "想知道为什么吗
I said, "Well, do you wonder?
乔杜里医生说我需要一个稳定的环境
"Dr Chaudhury says I need a stable environment.
而这不是一个稳定的环境  你的花美男
"This isn't a stable environment, with your fancy men
每五分钟都要出现一次"
"popping in every five minutes."
她说  "他不是我的花美男"
She said, "He isn't my fancy man!"
我说  "他是你萌芽时期的花美男"
I said, "Well, he's your fancy man in embryo."
她说  "你知道我听不懂你咬文嚼字"
She said, "You know I don't know what that means."
我说  "你多大了"  她说"我不知道"
I said, "How old, are you?" She said, "I don't know."
我说"你知道  你多大了"  她说"我不知道
I said, "You do. How old are you?" She said, "I don't.
你告诉我"  我说  "你72岁了"
"Tell me." I said, "You're 72."
"那也没多老"
"Well, that's not so old.
"温斯顿·丘吉尔年纪多大"
"How old was Winston Churchill?"
我说"什么时候"
I said, "When?"
她说"你以为你比我厉害  格雷厄姆·惠特克
She said, "You think you've got it over me, Graham Whittaker.
我告诉你吧  和弗兰克在一起的时候我脑子很清楚
"Well, I'll tell you something, my memory's better with Frank.
他会跟我谈经济
"He was telling me about the economy.
你全都搞错了"
"You've got it all wrong."
我说  "怎么呢"
I said, "How?"
"我记不清了  但你记得
"I can't remember, but you have."
把问题都怪罪到政府身上
"Blaming it on the government.
弗兰克说是黑人的问题"
"Frank says it's the blacks."
我什么都没说  我直接上楼了
I didn't say anything. I just came upstairs.
当我等会儿再下楼的时候
When I went down again later,
她还坐在那里  帽子外套都没脱
she was still sat there with her hat and coat on.
我说  "你想给他织个茶壶套吗"
I said, "Do you want to knit him a tea cosy?"
她说  "我觉得他不喜欢茶壶套
She said, "I don't think he's the tea-cosy type.
我第一次见他的时候  他有一辆挎斗摩托车
"When I first met him, he had a motorbike and sidecar.
而且  我觉得已经
"Besides," she said, "I think it's
过了送茶壶套的时候了"
gone beyond the tea-cosy stage."
我说  "什么意思"
I said, "What do you mean?
她说  "格雷厄姆
She said, "Graham...
我这辈子的目的就是你能开心
"..my one aim in life is for you to be happy.
如果我觉得我死掉能让你开心的话  我也愿意"
"If I thought that by dying, I would make you happy, I would."
我说  "母亲  你去世不会让我开心
I said, "Mother, your dying would not make me happy.
事实上正相反
"In fact, quite the reverse.
会让我不开心
"It would make me unhappy.
况且母亲你不会死的"
"Anyway, Mother, you're not going to die."
她说  "我知道我不会死的
She said, "I know I'm not going to die.
我还要结婚呢
"I'm going to get married.
蜜月定在特内里费岛  吃你的药吧"
"And the honeymoon is in Tenerife. Have one of your tablets."
她倒了点茶
She made some tea.
我说  "你怎么能去特内里费岛呢
I said, "How can you go to Tenerife?
你在斯卡伯勒都要窒息了"
"You're smothered at Scarborough."
她说  "那有个四星级酒店  空调设施一流
She said, "It's a four-star hotel with tip-top air-conditioning,
早餐都是在一个长条桌上享用"
"you get your breakfast from a long table."
我说  "那你的肠胃呢"
I said, "What about your bowels?"
她说 "我肠胃怎么了"
She said, "What about my bowels?!"
"你不是说在莫克姆你的肠胃就时不时感到不舒服吗
"Well, you said they were unpredictable at Morecambe.
带着那样的肠胃去加那利群岛
"Get 'em to the Canary Islands,
会拉得到处都是的"
"they're going to be all over the place."
她说  "谁说加那利群岛了
She said, "Who's talking about the Canary Islands?
我要去特内里费岛"
"I'm going to Tenerife."
我说  "去了特内里费岛之后呢
"And what about post-Tenerife?" I said.
你想去哪里生活"  她说  "这里
Where are you going to live?" She said, "Here.
弗兰克说他会断断续续地出差
"Frank says he'll be away on and off on business
但是他想把这里当作家"
"but he wants to call this home."
我说  "那我呢"
I said, "What about me?"
她走进了厨房
She went into the kitchen.
"我们在想你是不是愿意回青旅住
"Well, we wondered if you'd prefer to go back to the hostel.
你在青旅住的时候很开心
"You were happy at the hostel.
你可以接触各种人"
"You rubbed shoulders with all sorts."
我说  "妈  这是我的家"
I said, "Mam. This is my home!"
她说"弗兰克说过  你这个年纪的男人不应该和
She said, "'A man shouldn't be living with
和自己的母亲生活在一起
"'his mother at your age,' Frank says."
你吃药了吗"
"Did you take a tablet?"
现在是凌晨四点钟  我还是不能入睡
Now it's four o'clock in the morning and I can't sleep.
外面停了一辆车
There's a car parked outside.
我看不到  但是我想车里有人
I can't see, but I think there's somebody in it...
在看着  就像他们之前那样
..watching, like they used to do before.
我觉得这一切都结束了
I thought all that chapter had closed.
今天早上我去了社区关怀站
This morning I went to Community Caring
在健康中心那里
down at the health centre.
它为各种人提供所需
It caters for...all sorts.
经营者史蒂夫竭力反对
Steve, who runs it, is dead against
他所谓的贫民窟方法
what he calls the "ghetto approach".
他所追求的是性格难题的
What he's after is a nice mix of personality
完美结合  作为解决问题的最富有成效的练习
difficulties as being the most fruitful exercise in
和一个更现实的普遍性社会模型
problem-solving and a more realistic model of society generally.
那里有源源不断的咖啡
There's a constant flow of coffee -
史蒂夫称之为  给车轮加油
"oiling the wheels", Steve calls it -
会鼓励每个人大声说出自己的问题
and we're all encouraged to ventilate our problems
通常会让大家不拘礼节随意发挥
and generally let our hair down.
我有时候会觉得有些置身事外
I sometimes feel a bit out of it,
因为我从来没有什么特别的
as I've never had any particular
问题  所以这个时候  当史蒂夫说"好了
problems, so this time, when Steve says, "Right,
兄弟姐妹们  谁想来打头阵"
"chaps and chappesses, who'd like to set the ball rolling?"
我第一个跟他们说了母亲和特恩布尔先生的事情
I get in quick and tell them about Mother and Mr Turnbull.
当我说完  史蒂夫说道
When I'd finished Steve said,
"谢谢你  格雷厄姆  给我们分享你的问题
"Thank you, Graham, for sharing your problem with us.
有没有人想来交流心得的"
"Does anybody want to kick it around?"
第一个跑题的是伦纳德  他想知道
First off the mark is Leonard, who wonders
格雷厄姆是不是能完全理解
whether Graham has fully appreciated
老年人也可以坠入爱河
that old people can fall in love
也可以拥有真挚的感情经历
and have meaningful relationships,
总而言之就是  他们和年轻人一样
generally, the same as young people.
我认为这话从伦纳德嘴里说出是可以理解的
I suppose this is understandable coming from Leonard,
因为他已经65了  但却没有体会过真挚的感情
because he's 65, only he doesn't have meaningful relationships.
他曾经在维特罗斯超市门口暴露私处而被传讯
He's been had up for exposing himself in Waitrose doorway.
就像母亲说的  "乐购超市嘛  可以理解"
As Mother said, "Tesco, you could understand it."
然后贾尼斯插嘴道
Then Janice chips in.
"他们有过性交往吗"
"Had they been having sexual intercourse?"
我说  "我并不想讨论这个"
I said I didn't want to talk about it.
史蒂夫说  "为什么"  我说"我也不知道"
Steve said, "Why?" I said...I didn't know.
史蒂夫说"也许我们该讨论的是为什么格雷厄姆
Steve said, "Maybe what we should be talking about is why Graham
在性交往上如此有戒备心"
"is being so defensive about sexual intercourse."
我说  "史蒂夫
I said, "Steve.
我不是对性交往有戒备心
"I'm not being defensive about sexual intercourse.
她是我的母亲"
"She is my mother."
十分之九是女同的杰基说"格雷厄姆
And Jackie, who's nine parts lesbian, said, "Graham -
她也是个女人"
"she's also a woman."
我简直不敢相信
I couldn't believe this.
我说"杰基  你以前受过家暴
I said, "Jackie, you're an ex-battered wife.
我以为你并不赞成婚姻"
"I thought you didn't approve of marriage."
她说  "格雷厄姆  我赞成有爱的婚姻"
She said, "Graham, I approve of caring marriage."
我说  "杰基  这并不是有爱的婚姻"
I said, "Jackie, this is not caring marriage."
她说"格雷厄姆  特内里费岛是什么  是爱
She said, "Graham, what's Tenerife? That's caring.
我只有乌青的眼圈和一天的弗利特伍德之旅"
"All I got was a black eye and a day trip to Fleetwood."
然后他们都开始抨击我
Then they all had a go.
"帮助格雷厄姆"
"Get Graham."
史蒂夫总结说
Steve summed up.
"这个群体的普遍感受是
"The general feeling of the group
格雷厄姆可以更开放一些"
is that Graham could be more open."
我说  "我怎么才能更开放
I said, "How can I be more open?
有人坐在房子外面盯着我"
"There is somebody sat outside the house watching."
我想讨论那件事  可伦纳德跳出来说
I wanted to discuss that, only Leonard leapt in and said
他觉得有必要讨论一个
he felt the need to discuss an episode
英国家用品商店背后的轶事
behind British Home Stores.
我坚持了一会儿  然后就回家了
I stuck it a bit longer, then came home.
母亲坐在那里
Mother's sat there...
盛装打扮
..all dolled up.
戴着耳环  雪纺围巾  化着浓妆
Earrings on, chiffon scarf, lathered in make-up.
她说  "我还以为你是特恩布尔先生"  我说"不是"
"Oh," she says, "I thought you were Mr Turnbull." I said, "No."
她说  "我要去洗手间"
She said, "I'll just go to the lav."
接下来的十分钟她去了三次洗手间
She goes three times in the next ten minutes.
我说  "你不是今天就要结婚了吧"
I said, "You're not getting married
她说  "没有
today, are you?" She said, "No.
宾利有一家新的阿斯达超市开张了
"There's a new Asda superstore opened at Bingley.
我们想我们应该把它逛一遍
"We thought we'd give it the once-over.
弗兰克说他们有各种各样的防晒霜可供选择"
"Frank said they have a very good selection of sun tan lotions."
我说  "母亲
I said, "Mother...
有人在盯着这栋房子"
"..there's somebody watching the house."
她说  "我想买点面巾纸
She said, "I want to pick out some tissues
弗兰克在找点麂皮来装配他的挡风玻璃
"and Frank's looking for a little chamois for his windscreen.
他答应给我买一种叫芝士汉堡的东西
"He's promised me something called a cheeseburger,
那个大超市里有一个咖啡店"
"there's a cafe that's part of the complex."
这时  响起了喇叭的嘟嘟声
Just then, there's a little toot on the horn.
她又跑去洗手间
She runs to the lav again.
我说  "别去
I said, "Don't go.
妈  不要离开我"
"Don't leave me, Mam."
她说  "我不会答应的  你是个成年人了
She said, "I'm not giving in to you! You're a grown man.
我的衬裙露出来了吗"
"Is my underskirt showing?"
他又按喇叭了
He toots again.
她说  "去读本杂志吧
She said, "Read one of your magazines,
给自己做一个荷包蛋"
"make yourself a poached egg."
我说  "妈"
I said, "Mam!"
她说  "冰箱里有块鸡肉
She said, "There's that bit of chicken in the fridge.
你可以把那两件衬衫熨了
"You could iron those two shirts.
吃一片药  给我们一个吻
"Take a tablet. Give us a kiss.
拜拜"
"Toodle-pip."
我走进里屋  在那里他们看不见我
I went into the back room... where they couldn't see me.
我拉上窗帘  坐在黑暗中
I draw the curtains, and I'm sitting there in the dark...
直到我好像听到了敲门声
..when I think I hear a knock at the door.
我一动不动
I don't move...
又一阵更大的敲门声
..and there's another knock, louder.
我像乔杜里医生说的那样  告诉自己这不是真的
I do like Dr Chaudhury says and tell myself it's not happening,
可惜事与愿违
only it is.
有人透过信箱大喊
Somebody shouts through the letterbox,
"我知道你在里面
"I know you're in there.
开门"
"Open this door."
我就去开门了
So I do.
有个人在门外
And there is someone.
是个女人
It's a woman.
她说  "你是那个儿子吗"  我说  "什么"
She said, "Are you the son?" I said, "What?"
她说  "你是那个儿子吗  我是那个女儿"
She said, "Are you the son? I'm the daughter."
我说  "是你一直在监视这个房子吗"
I said, "Have you been watching the house?"
她说  "偶尔吧  怎么了"
She said, "On and off. Why?"
我说  "没什么"
I said, "Uh... Nothing."
她说  "我不知道穿什么看起来更合适"
She said, "I don't know what there is to look so suited about."
我说  "你还是进来说话吧"
I said, "You'd better come in."
当我听到外面汽车的声音时已经是九点钟了
It's nine o'clock when I hear the car outside.
我正坐着看电视
I'm sitting watching TV.
我说  你好
I said, "Oh, hello.
"玩得开心吗"  她说  "开心
"Did you have a good time?" She said, "Yes.
是的  我们很开心  谢谢"
"Yes, we did, thank you."
我说  "买到你要的防晒霜了吗"
I said, "Did you get your sun tan lotion?"
她说  "什么防晒霜"
She said, "What sun tan lotion?"
"你不是要去买防晒霜
"You were going to get some sun tan lotion.
算了不重要  你已经忘了
"Doesn't matter. You've forgotten.
特恩布尔先生怎么样"
"How's Mr Turnbull?"
"弗兰克吗  他很好"  她脱下了衣服
"Frank? He's all right." She took her things off.
她说  "格雷厄姆  我相信你会喜欢上他的
She said, "I'm sure you could get to like him, Graham,
只要你慢慢了解他
"if only you got to know him."
我说  好吧  那你应该带他进来"
I said, "Well, you should have brought him in."
"下次我会的
"Well, I will next time.
如果我们三个能时不时一起出门就太好了
"It'd be nice if now and again we could go off as a threesome.
你都干了些什么"
"What have you done?"
我说  "什么也没干  就坐在这里"
"Nothing," I said. "Just sat here."
"你没有不高兴吗"
"And you've been all right?"
"你知道的"  她说
"You see," she said.
"外面一个人也没有"
"There wasn't anybody outside."
"不是  外面有人"
"Oh, yes, there was."
"格雷厄姆  你吃药了吗  吃一片药"
"Oh, Graham. Have you had a tablet? Have a tablet."
"我不想吃药
"I don't want a tablet.
我告诉你外面有谁来过
"I'll tell you who was outside.
帕梅拉·马斯格雷夫女士"
"Mrs Pamela Musgrave."
她说  "那是谁"
She said, "Who's that?"
"娘家姓特恩布尔
"Nee Turnbull.
你未婚夫的女儿"
"The daughter of your hubby-to-be."
她说  "他没有女儿
She said, "He hasn't got a daughter.
他有一个儿子在南方  他没有女儿"
"He's got a son down south. He hasn't got a daughter."
她说  "你现在开始说胡话了  快吃药"
She said, "You're just making stuff up now. Have a tablet."
我说  "我没有胡说
I said, "I'm not making it up.
还有其他事情我也没有胡说
"And there's something else I'm not making up.
特恩布尔夫人"
"Mrs Turnbull."
她说  "没有什么特恩布尔夫人  她已经死了
She said, "There isn't a Mrs Turnbull. She's dead.
我要去厕所了"  我说  "她没死
"I'm going to the lav." I said, "She's not dead.
她正心碎地坐在轮椅上
"She's in a wheelchair with a broken heart.
他一直在骗你"
"He's been having you on."
过了一会  她从厕所出来了
After a bit she comes out.
"你不过是空口无凭罢了"
"You're just saying all this."
"便笺簿上有个号码  打过去
"There's a number on the pad. Ring up.
是他的妻子  身有残疾已经十年了
"She's disabled, is his wife. Has been for ten years.
他们的女儿在照顾父母
"Their daughter looks after them.
你并不是第一个
"You're not the first.
他经常这么做
"He's always doing it.
有个女人  本来要和他去巴巴多斯岛的
"One woman, it was going to be Barbados.
有人在博尔顿修道院发现你们在一起就告诉了他们
"Somebody spotted you together at Bolton Abbey.
真心祝福你们
"A well-wisher.
特内里费岛"
"Tenerife!"
过了一会  我给她端了一杯茶  她一直在哭
Later on, I took her a cup of tea. She'd been crying.
她说  "我买了这件小睡衣"
She said, "I bought this little bed jacket."
我说  "对不起  妈"
I said, "I'm sorry, Mam."
她说  "他一点没错
She said, "He was right enough.
在我这个年纪还想要什么  我年纪多大了"
"What can you expect at my age? How old am I?"
我说  "你72岁了"  她说  "还有一件事
"I said, you're 72." She said, "That's another thing...
我和他一起回记得
"..I remembered with him.
和你一起就会不记得"
"I don't remember with you."
我说  "对不起"
I said, "I'm sorry."
她说  "你没有对不起  你有什么好对不起的
She said, "You're not sorry. "How are you sorry?
你本来就不喜欢他"
"You didn't like him."
我说  "他配不上你"
I said, "He wasn't good enough for you."
她说  "配不配的我最清楚
She said, "I'm the best judge of that!
他潇洒帅气  比你强多了"
"He was natty. More than can be said for you."
又开始哭了
Starts crying again.
我说  "我理解你  妈"  她说  "你不理解"
I said, "I understand, Mam." She said, "You don't understand.
"你怎么会理解  你
"How can you understand? You...
你不是个正常人"
"..you're not normal"
我说  "我去睡觉了"
I said, "I'm going to bed."
过了一会  她在门外喊道
In a bit she comes shouting outside the door.
"你以为你比我厉害  格雷厄姆·惠特克
"You think you've got it over me, Graham Whittaker.
但你并没有
"Well...you haven't.
是我赢了你"  我说  "去睡觉吧"
"I've got it over you." I said, "Go to bed."
她说  "我知道你看的杂志都是些什么东西"
She said, "I know the kind of magazines you read."
我说  "国际象棋
I said, "Chess.
你会感冒的"  她说  "根本不是国际象棋
"You'll catch cold." She said, "They never are chess.
不穿衣服的国际象棋
"Chess with no clothes on.
一丝不挂的象棋  那种象棋
"Chess in their birthday suits. That kind of chess.
象棋男"
"Chess men."
我说  "回去睡觉
I say, "Go back to bed.
关上你的电热毯"
"Turn your blanket off."
转天  她完全好了
Next day, she's right as rain.
她已经忘了
She's forgotten it.
反正是不再提了  除了我们要
Never mentions it, anyway, except just as we're
出门的时候她说  "格雷厄姆  我真的爱你"
leaving the house she says, "I do love you, Graham."
我说  "我也爱你"
I said, "I love you, too."
她说  不管怎么说
She said, "Anyway...
"他要戴助听器"
"..he had a hearing aid."
她说  "今天的安排是什么"
She said, "What's on the agenda for today, then?"
我说  "我想我们可以去里彭看看"
I said, "I thought we might have a little ride to Ripon."
她说  "好
She said, "Oh, yes.
里彭  真好
"Ripon. That's nice.
我们可以去大教堂
"We could go to the cathedral.
我们喜欢古建筑  不是吗  你和我"
"We like old buildings, don't we, you and me?"
她挽住了我的胳膊
She put her arm through mine.